<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of the right reuerend father in God, Richard Senhouse, Lord Bishop of Carlile in the Metropoliticall Church of York, the six and twentith of September, 1624. By Richard Marshe Master of Arts, and vicar of Bristall in Yorke-shire.</title>
            <author>Marshe, Richard, d. 1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07061</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849273</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849273</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07061)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1490:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of the right reuerend father in God, Richard Senhouse, Lord Bishop of Carlile in the Metropoliticall Church of York, the six and twentith of September, 1624. By Richard Marshe Master of Arts, and vicar of Bristall in Yorke-shire.</title>
                  <author>Marshe, Richard, d. 1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Lownes for Matthew Lownes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An[n]o 1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ (-A1, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Senhouse, Richard, d. 1626.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14411:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14411:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE CONSECRATION OF THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, RICHARD SENHOUSE, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Carlile;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Metropoliticall Church of YORK, the ſix and twentith of September, 1624.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD MARSHE Maſter of Arts, and Vicar of BIRSTALL in Yorke-ſhire</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EXOD. 4.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O my Lord, ſend, I pray thee, by the hand of him whom thou wilt ſend.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by H. LOWNES for MATTHEW LOWNES. <hi>Ano</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14411:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14411:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST REVEREND FATHER in God, TOBY Archbiſhop of <hi>Yorke,</hi> Primate of England, and Metropolitane, my gracious good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MOST R<hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His poore thing was bred and <hi>borne</hi> in your ſervice. It might have had the hap to have been <hi>ſtill-borne:</hi> but now it hath <hi>cried,</hi> and was heard in as reverend, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, learned, wiſe, and in as frequent and as attentive an Auditorie, as ever ſhall be ſeen in theſe parts. It hath <hi>cried,</hi> and I pray God ſome ſay not, It was <hi>the voice of the Crier, preate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea nihil:</hi> yet many of beſt judgement (in love with it, before they knew what to call the father
<pb facs="tcp:14411:3"/>of it) will needs ſay, that it may live, and doe good. There are two things to help the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller; your <hi>Graces</hi> name, and the name of my Lord of <hi>Carlile:</hi> for, not a Prieſt, nor a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite, nor ſcarcely any other Paſſenger, when he obſerves the Preacher to be <hi>your</hi> Chaplain, and the Sermon to be preached at <hi>his</hi> conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but he will (though afterwards he neither wiſh oile to me, nor to my lamp) yet readily, like a good <hi>Samaritane,</hi> take out two pence, and give to my hoſte. If it may thus do good in Gods Church, I have my deſire, and farre beyond my firſt thoughts. God hee knowes, when I firſt ſpake or thought of <hi>ſending forth ſervants,</hi> I little dreamed of ſending forth a Sermon thus farre: but now I am glad of the occaſion, that thus thruſt forth into the ſervice of the church, I may withall profeſſe (by <hi>your</hi> good leave) my devoted ſervice unto <hi>your Grace;</hi> and let the world knowe, that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and unworthieſt Chaplaine, R. MARSHE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14411:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MATTH. 22.3, 4.</hi> And he ſent forth his ſervants, to call them that were bidden to the wedding; and they would not come. Againe hee ſent forth other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ſaying, Tell them which are bidden, Behold, I have prepared my dinner, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving elſewhere (not farre hence, nor long ſince) made entrance into this Parable, and ſpoken of the former Verſe, the marriage of the Sonne of God: the ſolemnitie of this day, and the frequencie of this Aſſembly (unto both which it was neceſſarie I ſhould have reſpect, when I knew my ſervice required in this place) both theſe (mee thought) might not bee ill fitted out of the words of this text, where God ſends his ſervants to fetch in gueſts to the wedding, to <hi>call</hi> and <hi>to tell them that were bidden &amp;c.</hi> For if wee have any thing in this caſe to <hi>tell,</hi> it is beſt to <hi>tell</hi> it in <hi>Sion,</hi> to publiſh it in <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and in the <hi>great City;</hi> and if we bee ſent to ſeeke and to <hi>call</hi> in gueſts, no place ſo fit as the <hi>great Aſſemblie,</hi> to call on the <hi>City</hi> before wee goe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14411:4"/>into the <hi>high wayes and hedges,</hi> here <hi>launch into the deepe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>let goe our nets, and make a draught.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the great buſineſſe now in hand (if you pleaſe to joyne the laſt Sunday with this) al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is but what the text here tels us, a ſolemne ſending of ſervants to call them that are bidden unto the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: yea, whereas there is in the text mention of two meſſages, <hi>ſending and ſending againe,</hi> ſending <hi>ſervants,</hi> and <hi>ſending other ſervants:</hi> ſo it fals out, as you had here the laſt day an <hi>ordinarie</hi> ſending, the <hi>Ordination</hi> of Miniſters; now you attend an <hi>extraordinary</hi> ſending, the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father: a ſolemnitie which we have not often ſeene in this place, an extraordinarie ſending of a more than ordinary (for manie reſpects, more than ordinarie) ſervant. He that runnes therefore, may reade ſome happie correſpondence betweene the worke of the day, and the words of the Text; that at leaſt for the Text ſake (however the Sermon prove) for the Text ſake, you may ſay, <hi>Sicut audivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſic etiam vidimus; As we have heard, ſo have we ſeen:</hi> and as we have ſeene, ſo have wee heard here <hi>in the City of our God.</hi> Indeed let no man doubt, but what God ſayes, hee will in due time performe, though it were a greater matter than eyther ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>ſervants,</hi> or ſpending of his <hi>Oxen and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> though it were the giving of his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne; that all men may ſee on Gods ſide, <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia parata,</hi> all things now readie. Oh that GOD might ſee us readie alſo, and that nothing were wanting, neyther proviſion, nor meſſengers, nor gueſts to furniſh that great marriage!</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14411:4"/>
            <p>The Text, thus ſuted unto the preſent occaſion, divides it ſelfe with the Aſſembly, part Clergie, part Laitie; Meſſengers and Gueſts.</p>
            <p>The Clergie are the <hi>ſervants</hi> ſent to call them which were bidden, and thoſe <hi>other ſervants,</hi> ſent with inſtructions to tell them that were bidden, <hi>Behold the dinner is prepared, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Laitie are the <hi>Gueſts</hi> bidden, and called, and ſtill called and bidden, expected and provided for, and ſtill provided for and expected. The Clergie are <hi>ſent,</hi> the Laitie are <hi>ſent for.</hi> The charge to the Clergie, is, <hi>Goe;</hi> to the Laitie, <hi>Come.</hi> It is the fault of the Clergie if either they bee not ſent; or ſent, doe not go; or going, doe not diſcharge their meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. It is the fault of the Laitie, if either they doe not receive us; or receiving, doe not heare; or hearing, will not <hi>come to the marriage.</hi> The text ſpeakes moſt of the Clergie, and if the Sermon (for once) doe ſo too, I hope no man will complaine; Complaine, ſaid I? no, you delight to have the Clergie touched, and it is for your advantage; for whether it be <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22</note> 
               <hi>all are yours, if you be Chriſts, as Chriſt is Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Clergie then, you have here, firſt, their <hi>Sending:</hi> he <hi>ſends,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſends againe.</hi> Secondly, their Title; <hi>ſervants</hi> and <hi>other ſervants.</hi> Thirdly, their <hi>Office,</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of their ſending, <hi>to call them that were bidden.</hi> Laſtly the <hi>Manner</hi> of their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to tell them, <hi>Sic dicit dominus, thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> For as they are ſent to call them that were bidden, ſo they muſt in calling, tell them nothing but what they are bidden. <hi>(And ſent ſoorth his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14411:5"/>ſervants).</hi> It is his goodneſſe to <hi>ſend,</hi> &amp; it is good &amp; neceſſary for us, that we be <hi>ſent.</hi> It is his goodneſſe to ſend, ſpecially if we conſider to <hi>whom</hi> he ſends; <hi>vocare vocatos,</hi> he ſends to <hi>them that were bidden.</hi> It was a favor once to <hi>bid</hi> them; now to <hi>ſend</hi> to them, is an eſpeciall goodneſſe: but what is it when hee <hi>ſends again,</hi> as it is in the next verſe? therefore of this more properly in that place where it is grown more ripe and full.</p>
            <p>And now nothing fitter to be obſerved than the neceſsitie of our ſending, that <hi>we be ſent,</hi> and have a juſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion to call in <hi>them that were bidden.</hi> For it were ſtrange if wee ſhould chance to bring in ſome gueſts, &amp; then the <hi>Maiſter of the feaſt</hi> ſhould anſwer them as <hi>Eli</hi> anſwered <hi>Samuel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>I called not, lie downe againe:</hi> Or as <hi>hee</hi> ſaies to one here at the 14. verſ. <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou?</hi> ſo <hi>he</hi> ſhould ſay to another, <hi>Friend, who brought thee in hither?</hi> That were much ſhame to the gueſt (it is a ſhame to take a lower roome, but <hi>turpius eijcitur,</hi> it is much more ſhame to be put out of the roome), it were a ſhame for the gueſt, and a danger ſure for the meſſenger:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.14.</note> 
               <hi>Quare adduxiſtis</hi> (ſaies <hi>Achis</hi>) <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have ye brought this mad fellow to me? David,</hi> that did but counterfeit madneſſe, eſcaped the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whileſt the ſervants, who were ſo mad to bring him in, got a rebuke. They ſeldom ſpeed better that are too forward; and it is likely they overſhoote their marke, that out-run their commiſsion, and are upon the way before they knowe whither to go.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 5.1.</note> Hee who requires us to <hi>take heed unto our feet when we enter into his houſe,</hi> would have us alſo to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14411:5"/>look as well to our <hi>feet</hi> when he <hi>ſends us forth,</hi> and neither to bring the <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> nor carry the <hi>meſſage of fooles.</hi> A meſſenger may be too haſtie; witnes the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> who brought the newes of <hi>Sauls</hi> death, and died for it:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.15</note> which <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> (it ſeemes) remembred, and therefore though hee would fain <hi>runne</hi> (when another was appointed) with newes to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 18.23</note> yet hee dares not without commiſſion from <hi>Ioab.</hi> For if it be deſtruction, to be over-juſt and over-wiſe (<hi>Be not righteous over-much, neither make thy ſelfe over-wiſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 7.16.</note> 
               <hi>why ſhouldſt thou destroy thy ſelfe,</hi> ſaith the Preacher?) ſure, to bee fooliſh over-much, to bee raſh, and too precipitate, muſt needs be the neck-break, the high-way, or rather a leap, than a way, unto deſtruction. <hi>Non amo ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miùm diligentes,</hi> might be written over the doore of God's Houſe: and we may well be jealous of them, who are not timorous in ſo great a buſineſs. The greateſt ſervants in God's Houſe, have been ſlowe and unready to undertake this office. <hi>Moſes,</hi> when God will make him a meſſenger of glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and deliverance unto his people, how did he ſeek by all meanes to bee excuſed, and (if it were poſſible) to ſhift it off! Firſt, <hi>Who am I?</hi> and then, <hi>Who art thou?</hi> and then, <hi>They will not beleeve;</hi> and then he wants <hi>eloquence:</hi> and when all impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are removed, and the <hi>rough</hi> waies made <hi>even,</hi> yet would hee faine put it off to another, with <hi>Mitte quem miſſurus es: O my Lord, ſend, I pray thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod,</hi> 4.13</note> 
               <hi>by the hand of him whom thou wilt ſend.</hi> Send any bodie, ſo hee may eſcape ſending. No wonder though <hi>Ionah</hi> ran away, rather than he would carry a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14411:6"/>of deſtruction to <hi>Niniveh,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> was thus loth to carry the meſſage of deliverance unto God's owne people. Would you ſee any others ſent forth and ſet forward?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 6. <hi>Ieremie</hi> 1.</note> Look and ſee <hi>Eſay</hi> cry out of <hi>polluted lips; Ieremie,</hi> that he is <hi>a childe, and cannot ſpeak.</hi> One for all (the Apoſtle, who had had his part in this Miniſtration above all his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows) cries,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16</note> 
               <hi>Ad haec quis? Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> Surely none, unleſſe he bee <hi>ſent.</hi> But and if yee conſider the weightineſſe of the office, <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> (you wil ſay) is too little: he muſt command and charge them,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Timothie</hi> 4</note> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> doth <hi>Timothie:</hi> hee muſt encourage them, as hee did <hi>Moſes;</hi> enable them, as hee did <hi>Eſay;</hi> imbolden them, as hee did <hi>Ezechiel. Sending</hi> is too little: hee had more need to <hi>lead</hi> them by the hand, as hee doth his people; or <hi>beare</hi> them in his armes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſe</hi> 11.8.</note> as <hi>Ephraim. Sending</hi> is too little: and therefore it is in the Text, not a ſimple <hi>ſending;</hi> but <hi>emittere,</hi> to <hi>ſend</hi> them <hi>foorth;</hi> that's ſomewhat more: and yet there is a better word to this purpoſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9. <hi>Extrudere, to thrust out labourers into his harveſt.</hi> He muſt do with his ſervants, if there be no remedy, as hee doth with his gueſts, <hi>compell</hi> the one to come in, and the other to go out. It was too cold a temper (perhaps) for a Souldier and a Generall, but very fit (me thinks) for a Prieſt or a Preacher to ſay to the Spirit of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudges</hi> 4.8.</note> as <hi>Barak</hi> ſaid to <hi>Deborah, If thou wilt go with me, then will I go: but if thou wilt not go with mee, I will not go.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To bee an Ambaſſadour in the affaires of Princes, is not for every man: nor is every man
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14411:6"/>fit to be Ambaſſador &amp; Orator for the Almightie, and for Chriſt, and in Chriſt's ſtead to negotiate his marriage. <hi>Are all Apostles? Are all Prophets? Are all Teachers?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15</note> No man (ſure) may take this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to himſelf, but he that is <hi>called</hi> of God: nor can any man preach, except he be <hi>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a confeſſed truth of all hands: but (I knowe not how) truths that are for proofe moſt eaſily confeſſed, are for practice oftentimes as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily neglected. For, notwithſtanding the burden of our calling, there hath been complaint made of old (I wiſh it doe not concerne us in theſe Times), that men would ruſh into this profeſſion, as if it were into the Poole of <hi>Betheſda;</hi> where the firſt come was beſt ſerved. They runne <hi>ad Sacerdotium, ad Epiſcopatum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Policraticus,</hi> as if ſome Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer had made ſolemne Proclamation, <hi>Occupet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremum ſcabies,</hi> The divell take the hindmoſt. If this bee the <hi>kingdome of heaven,</hi> it is in ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to be <hi>taken by violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee envie not the number: wee wiſh you were all a <hi>Royall Prieſthood.</hi> Wee envie not the number: we wiſh that <hi>all</hi> God's people <hi>could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie.</hi> We envie not the number: but we adviſe men to beware what they take in hand. <hi>Nadab</hi> &amp; <hi>Abihu</hi> may not kindle ſtrange fire;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.2 <hi>Num.</hi> 16.32</note> nor <hi>Corah</hi> and his company ſuffle themſelves into the Prieſt's of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; nor <hi>Saul</hi> offer ſacrifice; nor <hi>Vzziah</hi> burne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe; nor <hi>Vzzah</hi> put forth his hand to the Arke;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.13 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 26.16 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.7</note> nor any man run God's Errand unſent. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains earneſtly (and that oftner than once) againſt thoſe Prophets which runne and ſpeak for him,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14411:7"/>and hee hath not ſent them. <hi>I have not ſent theſe prophets, yet they ran: I have not ſpoken unto them, yet they prophecied.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. <hi>23.21</hi> Ezech. <hi>13.6.</hi> Leo apud Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrat.</note> It was an obſervation, if not a law, of old; <hi>Indignus ſacerdotio, niſi fuerit ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus invitus:</hi> Hee was held unworthy, if hee were not found unwilling to this office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eccleſia ab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the Church is nothing elſe but a company called out of the world: and as the Church is <hi>called</hi> from among other men; ſo from others of the Church, are there ſome who have a ſpeciall <hi>Calling,</hi> to bee <hi>Callers</hi> and Meſſengers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and his people.</p>
            <p>Theſe (that you may knowe them, or at leaſt they may knowe themſelves) they receive Ability from God, Authority from men. Abilitie from God: I doe not meane by immediate inſpiration, and <hi>dabitur in illâ horâ;</hi> but by carefull education in the ſchooles of the Prophets: with <hi>Daniel,</hi> they muſt by books underſtand theſe things.<note place="margin">Dan. <hi>9.2</hi> See Ecclus. c. <hi>39.1,</hi> &amp;c.</note> For thus doth God vouchſafe ſome meaſure of thoſe many neceſſary graces required in ſo high a calling, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them whom he ſends: and then they that have Authority in the Church, finding ſuch Abilitie, doe by <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> mark them for this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and as it were <hi>digito monſtrare,</hi> point them out to the Church, that thenceforth they may knowe them for the meſſengers and <hi>ſervants of the most high God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>which ſhew unto us the way of ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They who finde in themſelves no ſuch abilitie, and yet would faine be meſſengers, ſhould bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to ſtay awhile. The church hath had as weak ones, I grant it: and I dare promiſe, that when ſhe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14411:7"/>ſtands in as much need againe, ſhee ſhall ſend for them, <hi>dictatores ab aratro; from following the ewes great with lamb, to lead the people;</hi> from the plough, to the pulpit. In the mean time, our Saviour's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is good; If they itch to be building, let them ſit downe, and caſt the coſt before-hand. <hi>Verſate diu quid ferre recuſent, quid valeant humeri:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hor. de art.</note> take no more upon you than you are able to beare. If their hearts indite ſome good matter, let them chuſe it <hi>aequam viribus,</hi> anſwerable to their power, though it be but <hi>implere locum idiotae,</hi> to occupie the room of the unlearned, and to ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.16</note> They miſtake the chapter: it was in the former chapter, not in this, <hi>Dominus opus habet;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.2, 3.</note> but heer the caſe is alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and wee are bold to ſay, <hi>Dominus non habet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> the Lord hath now no need to <hi>ride</hi> either <hi>upon an aſſe,</hi> or <hi>an aſſes colt</hi> into <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> It is pitie the Church ſhould give <hi>hands,</hi> where God hath given no <hi>feet:</hi> ſuch cripples were fitter to lie at the gates of them temple, to ask almes, than to go into the Courts, or climb up into the Sanctuary of the Lord. You knowe how wary God was in the time of the Law, and how he hath excepted againſt all defects or blemiſhes. Help then, <hi>you Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> and <hi>lay hands ſuddenly on no man, neither make your ſelves partakers of other mens ſins.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.21</note> The maimed, the halt, the blinde, may make <hi>guests</hi> in the later end: but they are very unfit to make <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as in the firſt place they ſhould be <hi>enabled:</hi> ſo in the ſecond place they muſt be orderly <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized,</hi> whom God ſends. The old vulgar Latine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14411:8"/>ſpeaks ill of the houſe of <hi>Stephanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.15</note> and (on my conſcience) it doth them wrong to ſay, <hi>ordinave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſeipſos.</hi> The truth is, they did addict and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote themſelves unto the miniſtery, but not <hi>ordain themſelves</hi> Miniſters: that had beene againſt all good order. Their ordination (if they had any: for ſome would fain deny it) they either had from the Apoſtle himſelfe (which is moſt probable), or from <hi>Apollos,</hi> or from ſome ſuch as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had left there with like authority as hee left <hi>Titus</hi> in <hi>Creet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Titus</hi> 1.5</note> to <hi>ſet in order things which were wanting, &amp; to ordaine Elders in every City, as he had appointed.</hi> For to what end did the Apoſtle leave ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with <hi>Titus;</hi> or give charge to <hi>Timothie</hi> to <hi>lay hands ſuddenly on no man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22</note> but to make choice of faithfull men, <hi>who ſhould be able to teach others alſo;.</hi> if,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 23.9</note> like <hi>Ieroboam</hi>'s prieſts, every man that would might conſecrate himſelf, or, like the Anabaptiſts, ſtill runne by revelation? The Anabaptiſts, in not diſtinguiſhing betwixt the time of miracles, and of a ſettled government in the Church, dreaming that ſhould bee a permanent rule in the Church, <hi>that if any thing be revealed to another that ſits by, he muſt have audience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.30</note> 
               <hi>and let the firſt hold his peace;</hi> thus running after revelations, and ſeeing vain vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, they have outrun their wits,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.7.</note> they have out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run the Church, and further made themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet for any ſociety of men. And though they have outrun us, yet ſome among us run faſt after them, who, ſo farre as poſsibly they can, diſobey and diſdaine them that have the overſight of the Church, and <hi>ſpeak evill of all that are in any eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14411:8"/>authority.</hi> Turbulent, ſupercilious ſpirits; to thruſt themſelves into office in that houſe, whoſe Order and Government they are before-hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to approve; that come into the church as <hi>Cato</hi> into the Theatre, to go out againe; or like <hi>Momus,</hi> to quarrell that they knowe not how to mend; or as if this marriage-feaſt were the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taures feaſt, <hi>unde nemo ſine cicatrice;</hi> whence, in ſtead of favours, every one muſt carry wounds &amp; ſcarres.</p>
            <p>I knowe well, <hi>facit hoc illos hyacinthos,</hi> this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them deare unto the people,<note place="margin">Iuvenal.</note> and <hi>hence</hi> (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) <hi>they ſuck no ſmal advantage:</hi> but the ſervants whom God ſends, are not ſo baſe and mercenary; nor doe they think themſelves ſent to pleaſe the people, who are ſeldome heart-whole towards au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but rather to teach and guide them by all meanes into the way of peace and of obedience. They therefore, who either are not duely <hi>ſent,</hi> or doe not dutifully demeane themſelves towards that authority by which they were ſent, muſt bee taught, that they who have authority to <hi>ſend,</hi> have authority alſo to <hi>call back,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11.</note> to reſtraine, and to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch as teach <hi>for filthy lucre things they ought not.</hi> The Weeſell, ſaith hee, lickt the File till her tongue bled: then thinking ſhee had got blood of the File, ſhee lickt on, till ſhe had no tongue: Let them ſpeed ſo, that with bloody tongues ſtill lick the authority of our Church. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I would they were cut off:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.</note> I wiſh but their tongues, or rather their talk than their tongues cut off, that doe diſquiet you.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14411:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And ſent forth his ſervants.</hi>] Sending is the firſt thing: their title, <hi>ſervants,</hi> is the ſecond; and it ſeconds well that which is ſaid of ſending. They are <hi>ſervants,</hi> ſuch as may not go unſent, no more than they may bee idle when they are ſent: they muſt give account both who ſent them, and what they have done for him that ſent them.</p>
            <p>But to goe on: They are <hi>ſervants,</hi> they are no <hi>lords</hi> over God's heritage,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3.</note> to doe what they liſt; nor is the inheritance their owne to uſe at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: but they are <hi>ſervants,</hi> ſuch as muſt both take paines, and give account, and then may expect a reward. And it is well that they are <hi>ſervants;</hi> hee might have had meſſengers which had ſcarcely been ſervants: but theſe as they are no abſolute lords, ſo they are no utter ſtrangers, onely to tell you you muſt go, but cannot tell you how, or to point you the way, and not to go along with you; but ſervants, houſhold ſervants, <hi>emiſsi, ſent forth</hi> (in the Text), and therefore ſuch as know the way in, and can guide you and bring you unto their Maſter's houſe, and to the place where you would bee.</p>
            <p>There are foure things chiefly required in good ſervants; Faithfulneſſe, wiſdome, diligence; and patience: <hi>Faithfulneſſe,</hi> to knowe what to doe, <hi>wiſdome,</hi> to knowe how to doe it; <hi>diligence,</hi> to keep doing, and <hi>patience</hi> is good in ſervants, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in meſſengers, ſervants <hi>ſent forth,</hi> that know not what afflictions abide them, or what may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them by the way.</p>
            <p>For the two firſt, <hi>what</hi> is to be done, and <hi>how</hi> it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14411:9"/>is to be done, the Text tells us in <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> The name of ſervants ſhall now only ſerve to ſtirre us up to <hi>Diligence,</hi> &amp; (if you will) to bring us downe alſo unto <hi>Patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As obedience is the life of ſervice, ſo <hi>Diligence</hi> is the life of obedience; and as Vineger to the teeth, and as ſmoake to the eyes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.26.</note> ſo is the Sluggard to them that ſend him: <hi>Sal infatuatus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.13.</note> he is like to <hi>Salt that hath loſt his ſavour,</hi> or dead Wine that hath the name of Wine, but wants the ſpirit. He who hath ſuch a ſervant, may ſay he hath gotten <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> weapon; in ſtead of a ſword or a ſtaffe, the jaw-bone of an Aſſe: an inſtrument for eating, but neyther for fighting nor for working. Eaſe and pleaſure belong to Lords and Maſters, Care and <hi>diligence</hi> unto ſervants and meſſengers; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour makes enquirie for ſuch a ſervant to ſet over his houſhold, as will <hi>give them their portion of meate in due ſeaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.43.</note> and will be <hi>found ſo doing:</hi> to be found ſo doing, requires a conſtant diligence. And if it ſeeme anie whit eaſie to give them meate only in due ſeaſon, heare what S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes (who was himſelfe in labours moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant) heare him with an adjuration (for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath none more earneſt) call for <hi>in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon.</hi> They are quite out of ſeaſon,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2</note> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-diligent,</hi> which run <hi>unſent;</hi> but in ſervants that are <hi>ſent,</hi> all <hi>diligence,</hi> all celeritie is but ſeaſonable, not to <hi>communicate with fleſh and bloud,</hi> nor <hi>tarry to ſalute any man by the way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>Apelles</hi> painted his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant with Harts feete, and his hands full of tooles, ſwift and readie, <hi>(Impera, &amp; actum puta)</hi> if you ſay,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14411:10"/>
               <hi>Go, he goes;</hi> or <hi>Come, he comes;</hi> or <hi>Doe this, he doth it.</hi> The name of <hi>Servants,</hi> is ſufficient to enjoyne us all care and <hi>diligence;</hi> but it addes unto our charge, if you aske <hi>vvhat kinde of ſervants?</hi> For looke what ſervants you can imagine to have greateſt charge, &amp; to them are we reſembled in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Is the Stewards place a place of charge and care? why <hi>let a man ſo eſteeme of us,</hi> the Miniſters of Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>as ſtewards of the mysteries of God</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>). Is the Ambaſſadors place a place of truſt and of travell, of <hi>diligence</hi> and danger? <hi>Now then we are Ambaſſadors for Christ</hi> (ſaith he).<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20.</note> Are the Angels <hi>miniſtring ſpirits,</hi> and ſuch as doe <hi>excell in ſtrength</hi> to do his commandements? They change places and titles with us, when they be ſent forth, to us they become miniſtring ſpirits, and we when we are <hi>ſent forth,</hi> what are we then but bodily An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? But theſe (the world will thinke) are places too eminent, over-loftie compariſons; Stewards, Ambaſſadors, Angels! who would not be <hi>ſervants,</hi> ſo they might ſerve in theſe roomes? Look lower, and you meete with Shepheards, Watchmen, Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Husbandmen, Fiſhers, Labourers, Meſſengers, and the like; theſe alſo the Scripture uſeth, to put us in minde of <hi>diligence,</hi> and even in theſe I may ſay, <hi>Brethren, you ſee your calling:</hi> God not only by manie precepts letting us <hi>heare our charge,</hi> but alſo by theſe frequent and obvious reſemblances let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us <hi>ſee our calling,</hi> and what it is which hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires at our hands.</p>
            <p>They are unprofitable ſervants therefore (nay, the beſt muſt confeſſe that they are unprofitable)
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14411:10"/>yea ungracious and unſenſible ſervants, who in this calling can give themſelves over unto eaſe and pleaſure, and both forget what they heare with their eares, and neglect what they ſee with their eyes, <hi>Oculis ſubiecta fidelibus,</hi> which ſhould move more and more ſtrongly, awake them from their Lethargie, &amp; ſupine neglect of their <hi>ſervice.</hi> Theſe <hi>ſlow-bellyed Cretians,</hi> who are all bellies, and ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hands nor feet for diligence, nor eies nor eares for inſtruction, have alreadie drunke <hi>Lethé,</hi> which (they ſay) is the firſt river of Hell, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment they ſhall proceede to the reſt of thoſe bitter waters and lakes that burne with fire and brimſtone. It is juſt to caſt ſuch ſleepers into ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkeneſſe, there to ſleepe perpetually, if they can have leiſure for weeping &amp; gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>With our <hi>Diligence,</hi> it is neceſſarie that we joine <hi>Patience.</hi> A ſlothfull ſervant, a <hi>ſlothfull</hi> meſſenger will deceive him that ſent him, but an <hi>impatient</hi> meſſenger will trouble both him that ſent him, and them to whom he is ſent. An unquiet, <hi>impatient</hi> meſſenger is like <hi>Moſes</hi> rod,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.3.</note> a rod when hee laid it downe, and a ſerpent when he ſhould take it up; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make him ſtart and flye from it. It is no good veſſell for this heavenly treaſure, which is of ſo hot a temper; nor anie good clay for theſe veſſels, which will ſay unto the Potter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.20.</note> 
               <hi>wherefore haſt thou made me thus?</hi> We muſt reſolve (if ever we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with comfort) to goe on in our meſſage, <hi>tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row honour and diſhonour, thorow good report and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill report.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11.</note> We muſt learne in what eſtate ſoever we are, therewith to be content, to give backe at no
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14411:11"/>perills, to ſhrinke at no wearineſſe, nor painfulnes, nor watchings,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> nor hunger, nor thirſt, nor faſtings, nor cold, nor nakedneſſe: To be troubled on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8.</note> &amp; not diſtreſſed; perplexed, and not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire: being reviled,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 412.</note> to bleſſe; being defamed, to intreate. They were too hot (they were too hote to make Pariſh-Prieſts) that preſently call'd for fire from heaven: Such meſſengers the Pope may ſend (to the generall and eternall ſhame of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome) into the <hi>Indies,</hi> into <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> and to the reſt of thoſe armeleſſe, harmeleſſe people, not to covert them, but to plucke up, to roote out, and to deſtroy; not as <hi>ſheepe among wolves,</hi> but as wolves among poore ſheepe appointed to the ſlaughter;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 8.1.</note> not to call them to the marriage, but to make ſpeed to the ſpoyle, haſte to the prey. Our office is to <hi>ſuffer</hi> with meekneſſe them that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie minded,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25.</note> in meekeneſſe inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance, to the acknowledging of the truth; and, whileſt we ayme at nothing but the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of our calling,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.15. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.41.</note> willingly both beſtow, and be beſtowed, <hi>ſuffer afflictions gladly,</hi> glorie in our infirmities, and <hi>reioyce to be found worthy to ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing for the Name of Christ.</hi> For we are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>his</hi> ſervants that ſends us, but (though I have all this while forborne to tell you ſo) we are <hi>their</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants alſo unto whom we are ſent: for <hi>vvee preach not our ſelves</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but Christ Ieſus the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>and our ſelves your ſervants for Ieſus ſake.</hi> Our Saviour, before hee ſent his ſervants, tolde them what they might expect; and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> a ſervant of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14411:11"/>chiefeſt note, tells us how he ſped.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> Our Saviour tels of wants, and diſtreſſes, and perſecutions; S. <hi>Paul</hi> makes it good, and tells what perills, what ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings (of all ſorts) he had paſſed. Our Saviour ſaies, he ſends us <hi>as ſheepe among vvolves;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us what Wolves he found, what Lions mouthes he eſcaped, what <hi>beasts he fought withall at Epheſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>after the maner of men.</hi> Our Saviour ſayes, <hi>we ſhall be hated of all men;</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>wee are made a gazing-ſtock to the vvorld, to men and Angels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> Our Saviour ſayes, wee muſt looke for no better enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement than he had, <hi>the ſervant as the Maſter;</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, <hi>we are made the filth of the vvorld,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>the off ſcouring of all things.</hi> Enough of this: but to qualifie it, take his concluſion in the next verſe, <hi>Non confundere, ſed monere,</hi> it is not to ſhame us, but to warne us. Wee have need of theſe warnings. A religious and an indulgent Prince bleſſes us with manie <hi>Halcyonean</hi> dayes: but if ever thoſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments fall, which both our enemies and our owne ſinnes and ſecuritie ſtrive to pull upon us, we ſhall then want comfort. Howſoever, we have need of patience, &amp; little hope or time is there for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſeeing we are <hi>ſent to call them,</hi> who ſo long as there are <hi>Farmes,</hi> or <hi>Oxen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.18, 19, 20.</note> or <hi>Women</hi> in the world to detaine them, <hi>will not come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are ſent to <hi>call,</hi> that's the <hi>end</hi> of our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: but before we come ſo farre, I muſt intreate you <hi>againe</hi> to looke upon our <hi>ſending;</hi> for he <hi>ſends againe</hi> (ſayes the Text) <hi>rurſus miſis alios ſervos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 4.</note> he ſends <hi>againe,</hi> and ſends <hi>other ſervants.</hi> That hee ſends <hi>againe,</hi> ſhewes a diverſitie of time: that hee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14411:12"/>ſends <hi>other ſervants,</hi> makes a diverſity of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, though there be ſtill a communitie and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in the ſervice.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the time; there muſt needes bee a <hi>Rurſus,</hi> a ſending <hi>againe,</hi> a ſucceſſion of Meſſengers whileſt there is a ſucceſsion of men: manie Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, that <hi>their ſound may goe out unto the ends of the world;</hi> and likewiſe a continuance of Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that <hi>may remember his name from generation to generation.</hi> Thus there were other Prieſts after <hi>Aaron,</hi> other Prophets after <hi>Moſes.</hi> Our Saviour hath promiſed to be with his Meſſengers <hi>unto the end of the vvorld;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> which, becauſe it cannot be true here of their perſons, muſt be made good in their ſucceſſors: and the Apoſtle tells of gifts given at the firſt ſending, which muſt continue to the laſt ending,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8, 13.</note> 
               <hi>till vvee all come in the unitie of faith, &amp;c.</hi> there muſt needes be therefore a <hi>rurſus,</hi> a ſending <hi>againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this <hi>rurſus</hi> cannot but ſeeme ſtrange: For, doth God value his ſervants, their doings, their ſufferings, their diſgrace, their rejection, their blood <hi>which is openly ſhed,</hi> at ſo ſmall a rate? or ſhall we thinke him ſo inſenſible of his owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, that he knowes not what diſgrace it is ſtill to <hi>ſend,</hi> and <hi>ſend againe,</hi> to them who were bidden once before? <hi>Ire iterum in lachrymas, iterum ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare rogando;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg.</note> as if he meant to ſpeed for his impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, &amp; ſo he may ſpeed, he wil put up anie indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, anie loſſe; he cares not what become of his ſervants, ſo he may have gueſts.</p>
            <p>He ſends indeed againe and againe in the former
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14411:12"/>chapter, in the Parable of the Vineyard; but that's another caſe: there you cannot blame him; hee does as you doe, ſends, and ſends, &amp; ſends (I would you did no worſe) for rent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 21.</note> and fruits unto his far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors. Anie man would do ſo: but for gueſts, as here, who would trouble himſelfe ſo much, &amp; not rather diſclaime them utterly; and if he ſent <hi>again,</hi> ſend to forbid them for ever, and <hi>ſweare</hi> unto them <hi>in his vvrath that they ſhould never enter into his rest? David</hi> ſend <hi>once</hi> to viſite <hi>Hanun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.</note> but his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants found ſuch entertainment, as when he ſent <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,</hi> it was to ſpoyle &amp; to deſtroy,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chr.</hi> 20.</note> to cut the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with Sawes, and Harrowes, and Axes, <hi>to deſtroy thoſe murtherers</hi> (as it follows here in this Parable) <hi>and burne up their Cities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſter</hi> 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> never ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for <hi>Vaſhti;</hi> but becauſe ſhee <hi>once</hi> refuſed to come, ſhe was for ever caſt off, and her eſtate given to another better than ſhe. God might have done ſo with this ſtubborne and ſtiffe-necked people: &amp; if he could not eate his morſels alone, he might have ſent <hi>at once</hi> for ſome others more thankefull; have let out his Vineyard unto ſome other huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, where hee might have fruits in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and have called them to the marriage, who would be glad <hi>to be refreſhed with the crums which fall from his table.</hi> Why ſhould he ſo farre forget himſelfe, as give them leave <hi>once againe</hi> to denie him, but, having neglected their peace, and the day of their viſitation, thenceforth have rained upon them brimſtone and coles of fire, and eyther not ſpeake unto them, or <hi>ſpeake unto them in his wrath, and vexe them in his ſore diſpleaſure?</hi> God is not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14411:13"/>ſo ſwift to take vengeance, <hi>Lenta ira deorum,</hi> ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance from heaven is <hi>ſad</hi> and therefore <hi>ſlow.</hi> God is content to <hi>ſend,</hi> and <hi>ſend againe,</hi> and not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them who are <hi>once</hi> his people, for a <hi>rurſus,</hi> or an <hi>iterum.</hi> Yea, that which is but <hi>iterum</hi> here, in the next chapter growes to a <hi>Quoties, how often vvould I have gathered thy children together?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 23.37</note> And <hi>quoties</hi> is not much now, for it was at <hi>quid ultra</hi> long agoe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>vvhat could be done more for the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, that I have not done for it? Iterum miſit, hee ſent againe.</hi> Hee is blinde, that doth not ſee God here make good what once hee ſpake of himſelfe, (nay he proclaimed it with manie words, that all the world might heare and take notice) that he is <hi>Multus benignitate, abundant in goodneſſe.</hi> It was goodneſſe to <hi>ſend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6.</note> but <hi>abundant</hi> goodneſſe to <hi>ſend ſo often.</hi> ſo often, ſo <hi>long</hi> to ſtand at the doore and knocke, as if he would waite their leiſure, and ſtay thy tyde of their good diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>Any man will eaſily confeſſe, that this was too much for God to doe unto the Iewes, and in the meane while conſiders not, that, <hi>mutato nomine,</hi> change but the name, and it is true of us. Or wee need not change the name, we are the Iewes; <hi>Wee are the circumciſion</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle). True in regard of the favours of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.3.</note> transferred from them to us; and true alſo in reſpect of our diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and uncircumciſed hearts and cares, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee fulfill the meaſure of their iniquitie.</p>
            <p>I will not enlarge my ſelfe; onely let mee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand who is he amongſt us, that hath not given God leave to ſend unto him <hi>often,</hi> and to expect
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14411:13"/>
               <hi>long?</hi> or what meſſage can we expect from heaven (except the meſſage of a ſudden and finall deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) which hath not beene <hi>often</hi> tolde us by his <hi>ſervants?</hi> It were ſom eaſe (perhaps) unto our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, if we could conceive our ſelves to be of that number, who never heard of his will: but this torments us before the time, that wee <hi>know,</hi> and know that <hi>the ſervant who knowes his Maſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten vvith many ſtripes. Multitudo miſerationum fit magnitudo, &amp; cumulus damnationum;</hi> Manie mercies will pull on manie ſtripes, and everie <hi>iterum</hi> from him is an <hi>item</hi> to us, augments the number and meaſure of his favours, ladeth our reckoning, &amp; in the end wil adde weight unto our condemnation.</p>
            <p>And that a great deale more, if you conſider <hi>whom</hi> he ſends: for as it is <hi>iterum miſit,</hi> ſo it is <hi>alios ſervos, another</hi> ſending, and <hi>other</hi> ſervants; to take <hi>another</hi> repulſe, and that in <hi>other</hi> ſervants, aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates the offence. But why ſhould he ſend <hi>other</hi> ſervants? were not the firſt good enough, or wiſe enough, or fit enough to carrie the meſſage? Hee ſent <hi>other</hi> ſervants for his fruits in the former chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe the husbandmen dealt ſo rudely and ſo roundly with his meſſengers, as they that had gone <hi>once,</hi> were little fit to goe <hi>againe.</hi> That was no wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come meſſage, and they to whom it was ſent, were Farmors, <hi>rustica turba,</hi> ſuch as would denie <hi>Latona</hi> water,<note place="margin">Ovid.</note> if ſhe travelled by them, or the Iſraelites paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, or <hi>David</hi> and his men reliefe: but here the meſſage is full of courteſie, and the parties called to ſo great a marriage (wee might hope) had ſome more humanitie. It is poſsible therefore that there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14411:14"/>was ſome fault, or ſome want in the ſervants. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah</hi> ſent <hi>once,</hi> and <hi>againe,</hi> Captaines with their Fifties, to <hi>Eliah,</hi> but they ſped ill; they were too peremptorie, and ſtood too much upon the King their Maſter: <hi>The King hath ſaid,</hi> and, <hi>Thus hath the King ſaid;</hi> that would not ſerve. The third ſped by other meanes;<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.9, 11, 13.</note> 
               <hi>He fell downe on his knees before</hi> Eliah, <hi>and beſought him,</hi> and ſo brought him to the King. There is ſome choyce to be made of meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, eſpecially where the meſſage is weightie; and ſuch would be ſent as can diſcerne, <hi>quae molliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima fandi tempora,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg.</note> 
               <hi>quis rebus dexter modus,</hi> how to <hi>minister</hi> (I meane) <hi>a word in due ſeaſon;</hi> and not to betray the cauſe they have in hand, but ſerve the times nimbly, take hold on all advantages, &amp; ſhew themſelves ſuch as our Saviour requires, both <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>faithfull ſervants.</hi> The truth is, in this caſe, God left nothing unattempted to win them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.42.</note> or at leaſt to leave them inexcuſable: hee ſent unto them wiſe men, and Scribes, Prieſts and Prophets; he ſtill ſent them <hi>others,</hi> and change of ſervants. He ſent unto them <hi>all</hi> his ſervants (faith <hi>Ieremy</hi>) <hi>daily riſing up early and ſending them. Ieremy</hi> mends the matter well;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.25.</note> in ſtead of our <hi>iterum,</hi> he puts in <hi>quotidiè;</hi> in ſtead of <hi>alios,</hi> he puts in <hi>univerſos. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, hee ſent other ſervants;</hi> that's nothing: now he ſent <hi>quotidiè, diluculò continent èr</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) daily, early, continually, and all without exception.</p>
            <p>But are not the words of the Pſalmiſt (will ſome man ſay) true in this caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.20</note> 
               <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with other nations?</hi> Sure I am, we have no cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14411:14"/>he hath ſent to us <hi>again,</hi> and <hi>other</hi> ſervants: the Lord hath given unto us his Word, and <hi>great is the company of Preachers.</hi> We have ſtore of <hi>other ſervants,</hi> not onely <hi>alios numero,</hi> for multitude, but <hi>alios dotibus, alios gradibus;</hi> there is difference in their ability, and difference in their authority; in their gifts, and in their places.</p>
            <p>And firſt we have <hi>alios ſervos, i. aliter ornatos,</hi> men otherwiſe fitted, and furniſhed for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this meſſage. That Spirit which blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth where it liſteth, and diſtributeth to every one freely, and as it will, beſtowes <hi>diverſity</hi> of gifts for the gathering together of the Saints, and feaſteth them that are called unto the marriage, in the very calling, with the Manna of the word diverſly dreſt and ſerved-in. Feaſts are often not furniſhed with ſuch <hi>variety.</hi> The meſſage is the ſame in the mouthes of all God's ſervants. We have <hi>alios ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vos, alios nuncios,</hi> but not <hi>aliud nuncium;</hi> other meſſengers, but ſtill the ſame meſſage: yet is our delivering and handling of it alwaies ſomewhat different. As we ſay of mens faces, All are alike, and all unlike; <hi>Facies non omnibus una,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>nec diverſa tamen:</hi> ſo may you ſay of our Sermons, All bring the ſame meſſage; but whil'ſt every one ſtrives, according to his owne proper gift, to prevaile with you, it begets an admirable and moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing (it ſhould bee alſo a moſt winning) <hi>varietie,</hi> which makes the Word taſte like whatſoever you can deſire. We have them that pipe, and we have them that weep; them that wil eat with publicans and ſinners, and them who are more auſtere. We
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14411:15"/>have ſonnes of thunder, and ſons of conſolation; ſome from Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> with the terrours of the Law, and others from Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> with the joies of heaven; ſome bitter and ſharp (like <hi>Archilochus</hi> or <hi>Hipponax</hi> with their Iambicks), able to make an obſtinate ſinner hang himſelf,<note place="margin">Hor.</note> 
               <hi>qualis Lycambae ſpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus infido gener, aut acer hoſtis Bupalo;</hi> others, whoſe diſcourſe falls like raine into a fleece of wooll, or <hi>quale ſopor feſsis in gramine,</hi> as ſleep upon a weary traveller. Wee have ſome ſo fluent, as if they had lately drunk new wine; others ſo plaine and homely, as if they expected no other reward but a cup of cold water: ſome abundant in labors; ſome eloquent and mighty in the Scriptures: ſom, with <hi>Amos,</hi> fitted for Heardſmen; and ſome, with <hi>Eſay,</hi> for the Court; able <hi>to bind Princes in chains, and Nobles in links of iron.</hi> Some for planting, ſome for watering: ſome skilfull Maſter-builders, to lay a foundation; others to build up the houſe, or to trim up the building. <hi>Inſtant ardentes Tyrij,</hi> all as buſie as Bees in prayer with God, in conflict with the adverſary, in diſcourſe with the people, doe you not ſee how we ſweate in the worke? ſo as it muſt needs be confeſſed, that <hi>if our Goſpell bee</hi> yet <hi>hid, it is hid to them that periſh;</hi> and if the gueſts will not come,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3.</note> it is becauſe they will not, not becauſe they have not had <hi>other ſervants,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> have tried all waies to winne them, and to bring them to the wedding. Diverſity of gifts, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of adminiſtration, heapes of Teachers, flocks of companions; the Word preached in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and out of ſeaſon; the meat fitted for everie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14411:15"/>pallat, and made ſavorie, ſuch as your ſoules can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but love; milk for ſome, and ſtronger meat for others: our calling adorned in everie one (if yee would but ſee it) eyther with gravitie, or zeale, or ſocietie, or ſimplicitie, or learning, or happineſſe of invention, or ſtrength of judgement, or faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of memorie, or gracefulneſſe of deliverie; ſomething or other, I ſay (if you would but ſee it) to commend the meſſenger, &amp; to further the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage; muſt make you all confeſſe, that the fault is not in him that ſends, nor yet ſo much as the world would have it imagined, in them that are ſent in ſuch abundance and varietie.</p>
            <p>How chances it then that we ſpeed no better? I will tell you: We can ſpeake; but (alas!) to what end is it? to beate the ayre? We can write; but to what end ſhould we ſtand writing in the duſt, for the winde to ſcatter it, or frame our letters upon the gliding water? Our calls, our exhortations flie in the winde like <hi>Sibillaes</hi> Oracles: our Sermons are like Songs in the night, you will heare a little, but not loſe your ſleepe. The Text ſayes, <hi>he ſends other ſervants: Ieremy</hi> ſaies, hee ſends <hi>all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents.</hi> The world thinks he ſends <hi>too manie: Your table is made a ſnare unto you, and that which ſhould have beene for your advantage, is an occaſion of your falling:</hi> you have taken a ſurfet of the meſſage, and can no longer endure wholſome doctrine: our meſſage is the ſame, and your entertainment is the ſame; all is loſt, all is ſpilt, becauſe we are forced to tunne up all our <hi>new wine</hi> into your <hi>old bottles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Againe he ſends other ſervants.</hi>] Other in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14411:16"/>and againe, <hi>alios gradibus,</hi> others alſo in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. the meanneſſe of the meſſenger is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times diſadvantage to the meſſage, and therefore in the former parable, laſt of all he ſent <hi>his ſonne</hi> to ſee <hi>if peradventure they would reverence him.</hi> And as the ſonne differs much from the ſervants, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſervants wee cannot imagine but there muſt be an <hi>imparity,</hi> and difference of degree. God ſends for his gueſts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 22.15.</note> as <hi>Balack</hi> did for <hi>Balam,</hi> yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, moe, and more honourable; ſome that are worthie of double honour,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17.</note> and whoſe office it is to rule well, as well as to labour in the Word &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and to have the rule over you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17.</note> as well as to ſpeake unto you the word of God. For <hi>ſending,</hi> and <hi>ſending againe,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſervants,</hi> &amp; <hi>other ſervants,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtill ſervants</hi> in the plurall number; to let us know, that they are <hi>many</hi> whom he ſends: who (unleſſe hee wipe his noſe upon his ſleeve) would imagine as <hi>paritie,</hi> an <hi>iſotimie</hi> among ſo <hi>many?</hi> God is the God of order, and <hi>parity</hi> is the mother of confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; confuſion, of deſtruction. Oh let it fall upon the enemies of God, that ſo their forces, diſtracted and diſordered, may be ſoone defeated, whileſt Gods Church is alwayes <hi>acies ordinata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.</note> as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie under Banners, where order is moſt ſerverely kept, and who repoſe much (much of their ſafety) in their diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Thus under the Law, <hi>it is well ſeene how thou, my God, wentest in the Sanctuary.</hi> There were Levites under Prieſts,<note place="margin">Vid. Num. <hi>3. 1.</hi> Chron. <hi>24.</hi> Nehem. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; Matt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and Prieſts above Prieſts, and one high Prieſt over all that Province (I thinke wee could be content to yeeld the Pope ſo much, but
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14411:16"/>
               <hi>vaſtos non implet hiatus,</hi> a Province, or a Patriarch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will not ſerve him) Prince of the Princes of <hi>Levi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 3.32.</note> and above all the Iudges in Ieruſalem, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prieſts or ſecular,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.</note> in all matters of the Lord. And this authoritie (by your leave) he had for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; government, and not as a type of Chriſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall and judiciarie power, who was not a Prieſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> but of <hi>Melchiſedech.</hi> Now as there was diſtinction and degrees in the Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Clergie, where ſome had authoritie to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, others a neceſſity to obey, &amp; every one kept his diſtance: ſo it cannot be otherwiſe among the Miniſters of the new Covenant; but having gifts <hi>differing,</hi> according to the grace given, ſome muſt <hi>wayte</hi> on their miniſtring,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 8.</note> and ſome <hi>rule</hi> with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: and as among the gueſts, ſome are advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with <hi>Friend, ſit up higher;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 14.10.</note> ſo among the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants which fetch in the gueſts, ſome ſtand higher and neerer their Maſter: and if anie will <hi>exalt himſelfe,</hi> he muſt be made, with ſhame, to take a lower roome.</p>
            <p>This <hi>difference</hi> in authoritie and degree, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie both for the gueſts, and for the meſſengers. For the gueſts, it is neceſſary there ſhould be ſome enabled to raiſe up ſeede to their dead brethren, and that the Church ſhould have children inſtead of their Fathers (they were no children, but fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who firſt applyed theſe words of the Pſalme to this purpoſe) <hi>whom ſhee may make Princes in all lands.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Hieron.</note> And further, that ſome ſhould have the keyes of diſcipline, to ſee that holy things be not caſt to Dogs; to <hi>come</hi> among offendors with a <hi>rod,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14411:17"/>to <hi>cut off</hi> ſuch as are <hi>unquiet,</hi> to <hi>deliver them</hi> that are ſcandalous,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5 <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.9</note> to <hi>Satan,</hi> and by all meanes to provide that a little leaven doe not ſowre the whole lump.</p>
            <p>And as for the gueſts, ſo for the meſſengers, <hi>quis custodiet ipſos cuſtodes,</hi> is a good queſtion in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr:</hi> there had need be ſome to keepe the Keepers, to overſee the Seers; as in a great Harveſt there are ſome ſervants, who not only work themſelves, but alſo overſee the reſt of the labourers. Suppoſe the Labourers become loyterers; ſuppoſe there eyther want meſſengers, or the meſſengers wander from the right way; ſuppoſe <hi>pastores</hi> turned to <hi>raptores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. Pſalm <hi>144.8</hi>
               </note> ſervants and ſhepheards to theeves and robbers; ſuppoſe their <hi>mouthes talke of vanity,</hi> and <hi>their right hands</hi> become <hi>right hands of uniquity;</hi> ſuppoſe the Prophets become Foxes; ſuppoſe an accuſation exhibited againſt a <hi>Presbyter;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 13.4 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3 <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11</note> ſuppoſe ſome doe <hi>teach other doctrine;</hi> ſuppoſe ſome <hi>teach for filthy lucre,</hi> things they ought not; ſuppoſe there be ſome fooliſh queſtions, and contentions afoote;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.9 <hi>Acts</hi> 20.30</note> ſuppoſe ſome ſpeake <hi>perverſe things, to draw diſciples after them:</hi> muſt there not needs be a <hi>Timothy</hi> or a <hi>Titus,</hi> to give hands, to ordaine El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to receive accuſations, to avoyd, to prohibite, to ſtoppe the mouthes of ſome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15</note> to ſpeake, exhort, rebuke with all authoritie? There muſt needs be in the Church ſome who have both power of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination and juriſdiction to <hi>ſend forth other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> and to have an eye to their <hi>ſervice;</hi> to ſever ſome <hi>for</hi> the worke, and others <hi>from</hi> the worke; to appoint who ſhall carrie the meſſage, and to whom and by whom it ſhall not bee carried. Both theſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14411:17"/>parts of authoritie the Apoſtles did long retaine in their owne hands,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.20 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3</note> untill upon neceſſitie they muſt have both ſubſtitutes in their abſence, and ſucceſſors after their death: and then they did not onely make <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to adminiſter the Word and Sacraments; but alſo <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to <hi>ordeine Prieſts,</hi> and to <hi>governe excommunications:</hi> that ſo Ieſus Chriſt our Maſter, <hi>Angelus foederis,</hi> the great Angell of the Covenant, might <hi>be with them to the end of the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14</note> and <hi>Timothy</hi> might keepe this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto the appearing of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; not in their perſonall ſervice, but in ſucceſſion, and the iuſt deputation of <hi>new ſervants.</hi> Theſe two parts of authority do ſever <hi>Biſhops</hi> from the other <hi>Clergie,</hi> and ſet them as <hi>Stewards</hi> over the whole houſe: and as the <hi>Deaconſhip</hi> is a good degree to <hi>Prieſthood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13</note> ſo <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is but a degree to the office of a <hi>Biſhop.</hi> There may be ſometimes a <hi>community</hi> of the <hi>names,</hi> but that makes no <hi>confuſion</hi> of the <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices;</hi> nor can the <hi>Presbyterie</hi> bragge anie more of the names of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> than <hi>Biſhops</hi> may doe of the names of <hi>Angles:</hi> for to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> under the name of <hi>Angles,</hi> and to them only (as appeares by many cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances) doth our Saviour write, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>So if you ſhall heare that ſome good men of old have equalled the power of the Clergie, you muſt underſtand them of the Word &amp; Sacraments, and not of government; or when you ſee the <hi>Presbyterie</hi> lay on hands with the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> you muſt know, it is onely in <hi>attestation</hi> and approbation of his act, not any <hi>communication</hi> of his authoritie. And as for any allowance of names, it needs not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14411:18"/>trouble you; Cuſtome is the miſtris of ſpeaking: neyther is it the names, but the authoritie and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that hath beene queſtioned, of old, by <hi>Aërius,</hi> an aerie whining Heretick, who full of humane indignation to ſee <hi>Euſtathius</hi> preferred to the Biſhoprick, which hee, <hi>magis concupiſcebat.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Epiphanius</hi>),<note place="margin">Epiph. contra haer. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> haereſ. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> more earneſtly deſired, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to levell <hi>Biſhops</hi> with other <hi>Prieſts.</hi> And of late his old exploded error hath been revived by ſome fiery Reformers, who, finding much fault with the Popiſh Clergie, dealt with this ſo reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Order, as the Divell did with his damms leg, when he ſhould have bowed it ſtraight, he brake it quite aſunder: deſperate Phyſicians, that can finde no remedie for the head-ach, but to cut it off, and unmercifull Reformers, that will make the ſonne to beare the iniquitie of the father, and all poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſuffer for ſome faults in their predeceſſors. But the government of the Church by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>different</hi> authoritie of the meſſengers in our Church, as it is well grounded in <hi>Scripture,</hi> fairely builded in <hi>Eccleſiaſtick hiſtory,</hi> ſtrengthned by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the beſt <hi>Councels,</hi> and every where beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with atteſtations, and ſubmiſſive declarations of <hi>Fathers:</hi> ſo the ſtrength of it is much manifeſted by the oppoſition of the adverſaries. ſome of them men of ſpeciall note, and whoſe reputations (no doubt) win a great deale of credite to the cauſe, like the Elders againſt <hi>Suſanna.</hi> But as thoſe El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders did bewray themſelves, becauſe they did not agree of the tree; ſo theſe <hi>Elders</hi> (they love that name) are not yet agreed what tree ſhould ſhadow
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14411:18"/>us, nor what they would have in the roome of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops:</hi> ſome cry one thing, ſome another, and many of them that helpe to hold up the cry, know not (as it was in <hi>Demetrius</hi> tumult) wherefore they are come together.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.32.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is eaſie to ſay much in this caſe; if anie man love theſe warres, <hi>muſquam habitura triumphos,</hi> warres of trouble, and no triumph, it is eaſie now to ſay much, where a great deale too much is ſaid to our hands: the ſhot and powder ſpent on both ſides, might have beene better beſtowed upon a common adverſarie. but I may neyther goe on in <hi>this,</hi> nor goe off to <hi>that</hi> which followes. Let mee tell you, if God <hi>ſend other ſervants,</hi> and of <hi>higher place,</hi> hee lookes they ſhould be better reſpected, and that you ſhould obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> for <hi>they watch for your ſoules as they that muſt give accompt, that they may doe it with ioy, and not with griefe; for that is unprofitable for you. De nobis facile eſt;</hi> uſe us at your pleaſures: but them who rule both you and us, you cannot without diſprofite to your ſelves, diſquiet to the Church, diſcredite to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo eaſily ſlight and vilifie. <hi>Hinc dominicae vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum pacis rumpitur, &amp;c.</hi> Unitie, peace,<note place="margin">Cypr. de zelo et livore, vid. &amp; l. <hi>3.</hi> ep. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> charitie, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, all are loſt by this meanes, ſaith <hi>Cyprian. Cauſa omnium malorum;</hi> this is the root of all miſchiefes in the Church, ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> the contempt of Eccleſiaſtick authoritie, and diſobedience to <hi>Biſhops</hi> the God <hi>ſends</hi> unto us, <hi>other</hi> and <hi>greater ſervants,</hi> and they have all but little reſpect. What a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate ſlaverie is it in men, to feare and honour
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14411:19"/>Lords, and not to reverence their fathers?</p>
            <p>One thing more remaines in theſe ſendings of ſervants, and other ſervants; that ſtill <hi>all</hi> are <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants:</hi> what other <hi>diverſities</hi> ſoever there be, yet in this there is a <hi>communitie:</hi> whether they <hi>keepe</hi> the <hi>Keyes,</hi> or they be but <hi>doore-keepers</hi> in the houſe of God, they are all tyed to <hi>ſervice.</hi> Who then is <hi>Paul?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note> and who is <hi>Apollo?</hi> but <hi>Miniſters by vvhom yee beleeved, even as the Lord gave to every man.</hi> But I muſt make an end: My <hi>Lord elect,</hi> may this bee your <hi>memento</hi> in ſtead of <hi>ſic tranſit gloria mundi,</hi> or <hi>memento quòd homo es:</hi> the one hath beene uſed to Popes, to quench their vaine-glory; the other to Emperours, to put them in minde of mortalitie: in ſtead of any ſuch, admit this from the Text, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento quòd ſervus es, Remember</hi> ſtill your <hi>ſervice.</hi> This day you ſhall be <hi>ſent</hi> with a <hi>new Commiſsion,</hi> but ſtill to doe him <hi>ſervice:</hi> you ſhall be made <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other ſervant,</hi> but ſtill a <hi>ſervant.</hi> Your ſervice is changed, rather than removed; increaſed, rather than changed: you are called from the <hi>Pulpit</hi> to the <hi>Chayre,</hi> but neyther freed from the Pulpit, nor much eaſed by the Chair. <hi>Ad Cathedram, ad curam;</hi> the <hi>Chaire</hi> in the Church,<note place="margin">Bern.</note> and the <hi>Care</hi> of the Church, goe together: <hi>Whoſoever will be great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, let him be your miniſter; and whoſoever will be chiefe among you, let him be your ſervant,</hi> ſaith our Saviour.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 20.26</note> More <hi>ſervice</hi> here than <hi>ſoveraignety: ad Epiſcopatum, non ad Principatum;</hi> yours is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorall, a paternall government, not a Princely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, or compulſive dominion. We are all here ſent to call, not to compell them to come in. <hi>Non
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14411:19"/>ſic</hi> (ſaith our Saviour), not ſo as the Princes of the Gentiles, not ſo as <hi>Zebed us</hi> ſonnes, either with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie to uſe theſe places, or with ambition to ſeek them, <hi>Worthy of double honour</hi> from men;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.44</note> but ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely that honour that commeth from God. <hi>This is a true ſaying, if any deſire the office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, he deſireth a good worke. Worke,</hi> and <hi>Service;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1</note> but I crave pardon, your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> hath manie moe powerfull monitors, not onely <hi>within</hi> you, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from <hi>without:</hi> the heartie welcome of your owne <hi>countrey,</hi> the expectation of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> the promiſes of the <hi>Vniverſity,</hi> the favours of a moſt gracious <hi>Prince,</hi> will <hi>dicere Archippo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17</note> ſtill put you in minde to take heed, and to fulfill your Miniſtry, that he who findes you faithfull in a <hi>little,</hi> may in due time give you <hi>more</hi> authoritie.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 19.17</note>
            </p>
            <p>To you, all my <hi>brethren</hi> of the Clergie, enough hath beene ſaid both of our <hi>ſending</hi> and <hi>ſervice:</hi> yet let us not forget this, that ſeeing God is ſo dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in <hi>ſending</hi> and <hi>ſending againe, ſervants</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſervants;</hi> we ſhould be as diligent in diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meſſage, in <hi>going</hi> and <hi>going againe,</hi> trying all meanes, and calling continually, <hi>become all things to all men, if by any meanes we may win ſome. Et tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta curetur ſolicitudinequant a petitur ambitione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Policrat.</note> not more ambitious to be made meſſengers, than ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to diſcharge the meſſage. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, in a caſe where the Holy Ghoſt is verie punctuall to lay downe every circumſtance, <hi>Credo quia noluit nos negligenter audire quod ille ſtuduit tam diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter narrare;</hi> I do beleeve he is ſo diligent in telling,<note place="margin">Bern. uper Miſſus ſeſt.</note> becauſe he would not have us negligent in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14411:20"/>ſo ſay I; I am wel aſſured he would not have us to deliver the meſſage ſparingly, or coldly, when he ſends his meſſengers ſo carefully and ſo copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, unto you who will be no <hi>meſſengers,</hi> yet (I hope) would faine be <hi>gueſts;</hi> Let the multitude and <hi>variety</hi> of the meſſengers, the <hi>continuance</hi> of their ſending, the <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> of the meſſage, the <hi>kindneſſe</hi> of the Maiſter; let ſome of theſe, let all theſe move you, if not to count their <hi>feet beautifull</hi> that bring unto you theſe <hi>glad tydings,</hi> yet not to fill their <hi>faces</hi> with reproach; if not to give them <hi>double honour,</hi> yet not to entreate them <hi>ſhamefully;</hi> if not to make them <hi>partakers of all your goods,</hi> yet not to <hi>muzzle</hi> their mouthes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philem.</hi> 19.</note> Wee dare not ſay how much you owe us, we dare not tell you what you ſhould do for us; you have taught us to beare a lower ſaile: we only <hi>intreat</hi> you therfore to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear, &amp; ſtay your petulant &amp; laxative <hi>tongues,</hi> your ſacrilegious <hi>hands,</hi> your ravenous <hi>hearts,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> long to <hi>take the houſes of God in poſſeſsion,</hi> &amp; leave no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment for his meſſengers. I conclude: Then did the <hi>Church</hi> flouriſh, when the <hi>Clergie</hi> did only looke at the <hi>charge</hi> of their office, &amp; the <hi>Laity</hi> admire the <hi>dignity</hi> of their calling.</p>
            <p>God for his mercies ſake ſo fit us every one in our ſeverall callings, whether <hi>meſſengers</hi> or <hi>gueſts,</hi> for the marriage of his ſonne, as we may be knit unto him here by faith, and enjoy him eternally hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in glory, when wee ſhall no more be <hi>ſent forth</hi> from him, but <hi>follow</hi> him wherſoever he goeth; to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
